Guide to Joseph E. Burns Collection
Erie Canal Museum
Joseph E. Burns Collection
1909 - 1987
Personal and business items from Joseph Burns, founder of the Burns Manufacturing Company in Syracuse NY.
5 boxes
Burns, Joseph Edward, 1879-1942
Erie Canal Museum 318 Erie Boulevard East Syracuse, NY 13202
The collection is open for research use.
Joseph Edward Burns was born in Honesdale, PA in 1879. Burns was widely known throughout the country and abroad as a manufacturer and inventor of many machines and devices relating to cutlery and the cut glass industry. He started out as a manufacturer of cut glass and an instructor in glass cutting. For a time he had factories in England and Canada, and he traveled throughout Europe. In 1919, Burns patented a serrated knife which was the first of its kind and the foundation of his business, the Burns Manufacturing Company. The Burns Manufacturing Company was located alongside the Erie Canal on Water Street in Syracuse, NY. In 1914, the company established a glass cutting factory in Canastota, NY. Burns was also affiliated with the Norton Company in Worcester, MA.
Mr. Burns died on April 15, 1942 at his home in Syracuse, NY.
Erie Canal (N.Y.); Syracuse (N.Y.)
This collection documents the inventions and business activities of Joseph E. Burns, founder of the Burns Manufacturing Company in Syracuse, NY. It contains photographs, patents, product advertisements, and items which Burns either manufactured or used in the course of his work.
- Business Materials, 1909 - 1987
  - Burns Manufacturing Company, 1909 - 1987
    - FC 2019.03.50, January, 1964; Wooden award from National Housewares Manufacturers Association presented to Burns Manufacturing Company in recognition of the company's contribution to industry progress. (Box 4)
    - FC 2019.03.70, 1915; Photograph of Joseph Burns operating an abrasive grain washing and elevating machine which he invented. (Box 4, Folder Photographs)
    - FC 2019.03.60, Postcard advertisement for the Burns Bread Knife, Patented 8-23-21, with photograph of various Burns serrated edge knives. Burns Mfg. Co., Syracuse, NY. Handwritten notes in pencil on the back of the postcard. (Box 4, Folder Burns Manufacturing Co.)
    - FC 2019.03.61, Flier advertising a promotion special retail price of $0.69 for a Twin-Pak of Burns paring knives, including 1 serrated and 1 keen edge paring knife. The Burns Manufacturing Co. Inc., 1208 E. Water St., Syracuse, NY. (Box 4, Folder Burns Manufacturing Co.)
    - FC 2019.03.62, Brochure, titled The Burns Original Serrated Edge Cutlery, Open Stock, with illustrations of various cutlery and other products sold by the Burns Manufacturing Co. with holes punched for binder rings. (Box 4, Folder Burns Manufacturing Co.)
    - FC 2019.03.63, The Burns Original Serrated Edge Cutlery Brochure for open stock knives. (Box 4, Folder Burns Manufacturing Co.)
    - FC 2019.03.64, Brochure with illustrations of various cutlery sets sold by the Burns Manufacturing Co. (Box 4, Folder Burns Manufacturing Co.)
    - FC 2019.03.65, January 15, 1987; Brochure with photographs of Burnco cutlery and gift sets from 1987. (Box 4, Folder Burns Manufacturing Co.)
    - FC 2019.03.66, August 23, 1921; Copy of Specification of Letters Patent for a serrated edged cutting tool invented by Joseph E. Burns of Syracuse, NY. Application filed September 25, 1919; Serial No. 326,364. Patented August 23, 1921; No. 1,388,547 (Box 4, Folder Patents)
    - FC 2019.03.67, October 16, 1917; Letters Patent with official seal for marking devices--particularly for the marking of designs on glass prior to the formation of these designs on the glass by etching, cutting, etc.--invented by Joseph E. Burns of Canastota, NY. Application filed May 20, 1916; Serial No. 98,997. Patented October 16, 1917; No. 1,242,918. (Box 4, Folder Patents)
    - FC 2019.03.68, March 3, 1936; Letters Patent with official seal for citrous fruit tools invented by Joseph E. Burns of Syracuse, NY. Application filed January 25, 1932; Serial No. 588,677. Patented March 3, 1936; No. 2,032,562. (Box 4, Folder Patents)
    - FC 2019.03.69, January 14, 1941; Letters Patent with official seal for Apparatus for Finishing and Reconditioning Edge Tools invented by Joseph E. Burns of Syracuse, NY. Application filed January 27, 1939; Serial No. 253,189. Patented January 14, 1941; No. 2,228,385. (Box 4, Folder Patents)
    - FC 2019.03.01, Wooden box with hinged lid from the Burns Manufacturing Co.
    - Knives
      - Box 1
        - FC 2019.03.02, November 29, 1946; Hand saw which belonged to Captain E.F. O'Brien, 251 West Borden Ave. In use about 25 years.
        - FC 2019.03.03, The Burns Bread Knife. Restaurant shape No. 4.
        - FC 2019.03.04, The Burns Orange Peeler No. 111.
        - FC 2019.03.05, The Burns Double Edge Paring Knife No. 120.
      - Box 2
        - FC 2019.03.06-.19, 14 knives from the Burns Manufacturing Co.
      - Box 3
        - FC 2019.03.20-.49, 30 knives from the Burns Manufacturing Co.
  - Norton Company, 1909 - 1987
    - FC 2019.03.59, Five cardboard labels for Norton Grinding Wheels. (Box 4, Folder Norton Company)
    - FC 2019.03.58, Safety Guide for Grinding Wheel Users. (Box 4, Folder Norton Company)
    - FC 2019.03.57, Guide to glass cutting materials. (Box 4, Folder Norton Company)
    - FC 2019.03.56, January 8, 1918; Playbill for the Norton Minstrels for the benefit of the American Red Cross Affiliated Surgical Dressings Fund for the French Wounded. Travelers' Night at the Worcester Theater in Worcester, Massachusetts on January 8, 1918, presented by employees of Norton Companies. Joseph E. Burns pictured on p. 7 (Box 4, Folder Norton Company)
    - FC 2019.03.73, Leatherbound, three-ring binder containing brochures for Norton Co. products, other related business information, and Joseph Burns' business card. (Box 4, Folder Miscellaneous)
    - FC 2019.03.53, Case with six small glass bottles containing powders for grinding. (Box 5)
    - FC 2019.03.54, India Oilstone in leather case used by Norton Company (Box 5)
    - FC 2019.03.52, Wooden box labeled Pike Manufacturing Co. containing grinding wheels. (Box 5)
    - FC 2019.03.71, Group portrait of Norton salesmen. (Box 4, Folder Photographs)
- Personal Materials, 1909 - 1987
  - FC 2019.03.51, Leather satchel with initials J.E.B. (Box 5)
  - FC 2019.03.56, Framed portrait of Joseph Burns. (Box 5)
  - FC 2019.03.55, April 19, 1928; Framed patent in Swedish awarded to Joseph Edward Burns. (Box 5)
  - FC 2019.03.72, Small slip of paper used for voting. "AGAINST the Act to create a State Debt, to provide for the payment of the Canal and General Fund Debts." (Box 4, Folder Miscellaneous)